{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In this country, a rock garden with sculptures made from recycled waste and a steel sculpture of an open hand are found in sectors of one city. The first Prime Minister of this country commissioned Le Corbusier to design that planned city, Chandigarh. Another monument in this country is named for the colored sandstone it was built with when the capital was moved from Agra. For ten points, name this country where Mughal rulers once used the Peacock Throne in the Red Fort in Delhi.",
      "answer": "Republic of India"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group secured power in Chelmno Land after its natives agreed to the Treaty of Christburg. This group expanded operations in Prussia at the request of Konrad of Masovia. This group failed to take Pskov from Alexander Nevsky after being defeated on Lake Peipus in the Battle of the Ice. The influence of this group declined after losing at Grunwald to Poland-Lithuania. For ten points, name this group of German crusaders.",
      "answer": [
        "Teutonic Order or Teutonic Knights",
        "Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Development along the Tuolumne [to-all-um-nee] River in this state was unsuccessfully opposed by John Muir. The O’Shaughnessy Dam filled up this state’s Hetch Hetchy Valley in 1923. Glacier Point and Vernal Fall are located in a national park in this state on the west side of the Sierra Nevada mountains. Half Dome was photographed numerous times by Ansel Adams in, for ten points, what US state that is home to Yosemite National Park?",
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ban liang coin was standardized under this man’s chancellor Li Si, who forged a letter ordering this man’s son Fusu to commit suicide. This man survived an assassination attempt in which a blind musician struck out at him with a heavy lute. The ascension of this man marked the end of the Warring States period, and he was buried alongside thousands of terracotta warriors. For ten points, name this first emperor of the Qin dynasty.",
      "answer": "Qin Shi Huangdi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mary Dyer was hanged in this city, making her one of this city’s three namesake martyrs. In a lawsuit involving this city and its northern suburb, Daniel Webster argued against the Warren Bridge Company in the Charles River Bridge case. A 1773 incident in this city led to the Coercive Acts and began when men boarded the Beaver and other ships dressed as Mohawk Indians. For ten points, name this city where Samuel Adams led a disruptive Tea Party.",
      "answer": "Boston"
    },
    {
      "question": "This president rejected Texas’ first application for annexation. This politician led the Albany Regency, a group of New York politicians, and his supposedly lavish lifestyle in the White House was attacked by Charles Ogle in the Gold Spoon Oration. This man ordered Winfield Scott to carry out his predecessor’s Indian Removal Act, causing the Trail of Tears. For ten points, name this US president who succeeded Andrew Jackson.",
      "answer": "Martin Van Buren"
    },
    {
      "question": "This discipline’s focus was shifted onto social constructions, rather than observables, by Giambattista Vico’s verum factum principle. The “heroic” in this discipline was discussed by Thomas Carlyle, who developed a “Great Man” theory of it. Authors in this field’s Dunning School promoted a “lost cause” narrative of the Confederacy in school textbooks. For ten points, name this study of humanity’s past.",
      "answer": [
        "history",
        "more descriptive answers, such as “the philosophy of history”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The beginning of this event was signalled with the phrase, “crack the sky, shake the Earth,” and it continued in the May Offensive. One theory suggests the Battle of Khe Sanh was a diversion for this event, in which blacklisted civilians were buried alive in Hue [Hway]. This operation led to the infiltration of the U.S. embassy in Saigon by Viet Cong guerillas. The breaking of the Lunar New Year truce started, for ten points, what 1968 offensive that caused U.S. public opinion to turn against the Vietnam War?",
      "answer": "Tet Offensive"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2010, nine activists trying to bring aid to this territory were killed when their “Freedom Flotilla” was raided. This region’s southwest border lies on the narrow Philadelphia Corridor, which is patrolled by an Egyptian Border Guard Force. In 2005, all Israeli settlements in this region were vacated, as were four in the West Bank. For ten points, name this self-governing Palestinian territory, a strip along the Mediterranean Sea.",
      "answer": "Gaza Strip"
    },
    {
      "question": "The towns of Hastings and Rye received tax exemptions in exchange for maintaining these objects as part of a group of five protected cities. Sutton Hoo is the site of a buried, undisturbed one of these objects from the 7th century. Henry I’s son William Adelin was killed in a disaster involving one of these vehicles, which were used during raids on English monasteries. For ten points, name these vehicles built in Southampton and other English port cities.",
      "answer": [
        "ships",
        "boats",
        "longship after Sutton Hoo is said"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician attacked his opponent’s support for weekend furlough passes in the Willie Horton ad. In another ad, this man listed his opponent’s opposition to military bills while his opponent rode in a tank. This man called trickle-down economics “voodoo economics” before serving as Ronald Reagan’s Vice President. For ten points, name this man who reneged on his promise of “no new taxes,” then lost his re-election campaign to Bill Clinton in 1992.",
        "answer": [
          "George Herbert Walker Bush",
          "Bush the Elder",
          "Bush the 41st"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bush used the Willie Horton and Tank ads in his campaign against this Massachusetts governor, the Democratic nominee in 1988.",
        "answer": "Michael Dukakis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this dynasty, the heqin [huh-CHEEN] system of using marriages for peace was used to repel an attack by Xiongnu [shong-nu] Emperor Modu Chanyu. Sima Qian [see-ma chee-ahn] wrote the Records of the Grand Historian during the reign of this dynasty’s Emperor Wu. The Trung Sisters attempted to liberate Vietnam from this dynasty, which was founded by Liu Bang. For ten points, name this dynasty that shares its name with China’s largest ethnic group.",
        "answer": "Han Dynasty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Han Dynasty was followed by this tumultuous period, during which the warrior Cao Cao [tsow-tsow] was active. The Jin Dynasty’s conquest of Eastern Wu ended this period.",
        "answer": "Three Kingdoms period"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to myth, this nation was created by two gods named “He-who-invites” and “She-who-is- invited” and the help of a giant spear. This country is the birthplace of a religion that uses purification rituals called harae [ha-rah-ay] and whose holiest shrine is rebuilt every 20 years. In 1995, a doomsday cult carried out a sarin attack in this nation’s largest city. The Ise [ee-say] and Yasukuni shrines can be found in, for ten points, what Asian country where Shinto developed in the 8th century and is practiced in Tokyo?",
        "answer": "Japan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Japan, Shinbutsu-shugo is a syncretism, or mixed religion, of aspects of Shinto with this other world religion. The Zen school of this religion is also widely practiced in Japan.",
        "answer": [
          "Buddhism",
          "Zen Buddhism"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Duringthiswar,theterm“khakielection,”wascoinedtodescribeanelectioninfluencedbyanongoing or finished war. The Fawcett Commission was formed after Emily Hobhouse reported on concentration camps used in this war. Prior to this war, Cecil Rhodes sponsored a failed attempt to trigger a settler uprising, the Jameson Raid. The British established control over the Orange Free State and the Transvaal in, for ten points, what South African war named for the defeated Dutch settlers?",
        "answer": "Second Boer War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the failure of the Jameson Raid, the leader of this country sent a congratulatory telegram to Paul Kruger, infuriating Britain. Queen Victoria later received an apology from this country’s leader, her grandson.",
        "answer": "Germany the leader being Kaiser Wilhelm II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man authorized military intervention against Samos after Miletus asked for aid in a war for the city of Priene. This man secured power over his rivals, Cimon and Thucydides, through ostracism. This man described the greatness of his city in a celebrated funeral oration and hired Iktinos and Kallikrates to renovate the Acropolis. For ten points, name this leader of the Delian League and statesman of Athens during its Golden Age.",
        "answer": "Pericles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pericles controversially ordered the Delian League to stop accepting military support as dues and to take this financial action, making it easier for Pericles to renovate the Acropolis. Description acceptable.",
        "answer": [
          "moving the treasury to Athens leniently",
          "word forms and phrasings",
          "also",
          "mention of storing the money in the Parthenon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man refused to support the Scottsboro Boys as editor-in-chief of the newspaper The Crisis. This man’s Black Reconstruction challenged Dunning school ideas of Reconstruction as a mostly white phenomenon. This first African American to earn a doctorate at Harvard supported an African American intellectual elite known as the “Talented Tenth,” which pitted him against Booker T. Washington. For ten points, name this author of The Souls of Black Folk.",
        "answer": "W.E.B. William Edward Burghardt Du Bois"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Du Bois opposed Booker T. Washington’s idea, delivered in an exposition speech in this Southern city, that black Americans should “cast down your bucket where you are.” That idea became known as this city’s “compromise.”",
        "answer": [
          "Atlanta",
          "Atlanta Exposition speech",
          "Atlanta Compromise"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city is the site of an uprising where many of the Friends of the ABC are killed, but Marius Pontmercy is carried to safety from the barricade through this city’s sewers. In another novel set in this city, Claude Frollo is pushed off of a roof and falls to his death after laughing at an execution taking place in the Place de Gr`eve [plass de grev]. For ten points, name this city, the setting of parts of Les Miserables and a cathedral where Quasimodo works as a bell ringer in The Hunchback of Notre Dame.",
        "answer": [
          "Paris BONUS:ThisauthorofThe Hunchback of Notre Dame depictedthe1832JuneRebellioninLes Miserables. ANSWER: Victor Marie Hugo 8 In this city, a white monument smeared by black paint was relocated into St. John’s Cemetery after its removal from Dalhousie Square. A tragedy in this city was recounted in the writings of J.Z. Howell, who noted that nobody dared to wake the Nawab of Bengal. This city was the site of Fort William, whose troops were captured in 1756 and crammed into a tiny space. Over one hundred British soldiers were suffocated to death in, for ten points, what east Indian city’s “Black Hole?” ANSWER: Calcutta or Kolkata",
          "Black Hole of Calcutta"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned paint-smeared object was this type of monument, one of which stands in the middle of St. Peter’s Square in Rome.",
        "answer": "obelisk"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Colleges and Universities",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Oldest American university, which merged with Radcliffe in the 20th century.",
          "answer": [
            "Harvard University",
            "Harvard College"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Connecticut Ivy League school whose secret societies include Skull and Bones.",
          "answer": [
            "Yale University",
            "Yale College"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Oldest English university, whose 11th century origins make it older than rival Cambridge.",
          "answer": "University of Oxford or Oxford University"
        },
        {
          "question": "California school founded by Leland, a railroad baron, near what became Silicon Valley.",
          "answer": "Stanford University"
        },
        {
          "question": "School founded by John D. Rockefeller that will house the Obama Presidential Library.",
          "answer": "University of Chicago"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was known as King’s College and is the oldest in New York.",
          "answer": [
            "Columbia University",
            "Columbia College"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Second oldest US college, having been chartered by its royal namesakes.",
          "answer": "The College of William and Mary in Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "First college in the US to accept students of all races.",
          "answer": "Oberlin College"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Royal Houses of Europe",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Tudor queen of England who ruled from 1558 to 1603.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian royal house whose hereditary rule was passed to Maria Theresa via the Pragmatic Sanction.",
          "answer": "House of Habsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last French royal house before the French Revolution.",
          "answer": "House of Bourbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "French royal house founded by Hugh after the end of the Carolingians.",
          "answer": "House of Capet"
        },
        {
          "question": "German house that ruled a namesake state and Britain after the reign of George I.",
          "answer": "House of Hanover"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portuguese royal house that ruled until Portugal was inherited by Spain. It was eventually succeeded by the House of Braganza.",
          "answer": "House of Aviz"
        },
        {
          "question": "House that ruled a unified Italy after its namesake state united the peninsula under the prime minister Cavour.",
          "answer": "House of Savoy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Frankish house that ruled the Holy Roman Empire under Conrad II. It also names a set of Frankish law that only allowed for male succession.",
          "answer": "House of Salian or Salic Law"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Silk Road",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire that traded with China along the Silk Road, delivering coins and medallions depicting Maximian and Marcus Aurelius.",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Empire",
            "Rome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Animals found on mulberry trees, from which silk was produced in ancient China.",
          "answer": "silkworms"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire whose Royal Road, established by Darius the Great, formed part of the Silk Road.",
          "answer": "Persian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity that names the southern branch of the road and whose Oolong and Darjeeling varieties were traded along it.",
          "answer": [
            "tea",
            "Oolong tea",
            "Darjeeling tea"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where the Karakoram Highway follows the Silk Road to Abottabad, just west of Islamabad.",
          "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian peninsula whose Silla and Goguryeo kingdoms benefited from trade along the road.",
          "answer": "Korean Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inns along the Silk Road, named for the groups of travelers who would rest there.",
          "answer": "caravanserai or caravansara"
        },
        {
          "question": "Christian sect that rejected Mary as being the mother of god and spread to China via the Silk Road.",
          "answer": [
            "Nestorian Christianity",
            "Nestorianism and other word forms"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During his time as governor of Africa, this man was pelted by turnips and found himself in financial difficulty, causing him to turn to the mule trade. This man fell out of imperial favor after falling asleep during one of (20 pts)",
        "Nero’s lyre recitals. During the Great Jewish Revolt, this man threw captured prisoners into the Dead Sea to test its legendary buoyancy; that revolt was later crushed by his son (10 pts)",
        "Titus. For ten points, name this founder of the Flavian dynasty, the last Emperor during the Year of the Four Emperors."
      ],
      "answer": "Vespasian or Titus Flavius Caesar Vespasianus Augustus, but"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1967, this man argued that “it’s [the media’s] responsibility for spreading” the news that he had taken LSD, denying he had “encouraged” his fans to take drugs. This man was arrested in Tokyo for possession of marijuana in 1980, canceling a (20 pts)",
        "Wings tour and ultimately causing the breakup of the band. Drug-inspired songs like “Got to Get You Into My Life,” and “Magical (10 pts)",
        "Mystery Tour” were sung by, for ten points, what British singer who co-wrote those songs with John Lennon in The Beatles?"
      ],
      "answer": "James Paul McCartney"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. The U.S. agreed to end trade relations with one of these two countries if the other would grant safe passage to American merchant vessels by the terms of Macon’s Bill Number Two. The (20 pts)",
        "Non-Intercourse Act prevented American trade with these two countries, and commerce between the U.S. and these two countries virtually ended with the passage of the (10 pts)",
        "Embargo Act. For ten points, name these two European powers that vied for American economic support during the Napoleonic Wars."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "England and France",
        "Great Britain",
        "the United Kingdom in place of England",
        "answers in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Prince Johnson videotaped the torture of this country’s President Samuel Doe to prove he was not protected by black magic. Two women from this country and one from Yemen shared the 2011 (20 pts)",
        "Nobel Peace Prize; one of those women, Ellen Johnson Sirleaf, opposed warlord Charles (10 pts)",
        "Taylor, who was convicted of crimes against humanity for this country’s 20th century civil wars. For ten points, name this African country whose capital, Monrovia, was founded by the American Colonization Society as a home for freed slaves."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Liberia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An original proof of this theorem used trapezoids and was written during James Garfield’s Congressional career. Jamshid al-Kashi is the first recorded mathematician to find an extension of this theorem now known as the Law of (20 pts)",
        "Cosines. Euclid’s proof of this theorem relied on cutting a square into two rectangles and constructing two (10 pts)",
        "triangles with area equal to the rectangles. For ten points, name this geometric theorem often stated as a squared plus b squared equals c squared."
      ],
      "answer": "Pythagorean theorem"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2009, a group of firefighters in this state who had not been given promotions won their Supreme Court case, Ricci v. DeStefano. In 2005, Susette Kelo sued a town in this state for misusing its (20 pts)",
        "eminent domain power by seizing condemned property along the Thames River. In 1965, this state’s Comstock Act banning contraception was struck down after a lawsuit by Estelle (10 pts)",
        "Griswold. For ten points, name this New England state, the site of the Kelo v. New London and the New Haven firefighters cases."
      ],
      "answer": "Connecticut"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One composer from this country wrote a ballet about the Roman slave leader Spartacus and another work, set on a kolkhoz, that is known for a xylophone solo. The Mariinsky Ballet was renamed the (20 pts)",
        "Kirov Ballet in this country, where Aram Khachaturian’s Gayane included the “Sabre Dance.” In 1961, a dancer from this country became the first artist to (10 pts)",
        "defect during the Cold War. Rudolf Nureyev and Mikhail Baryshnikov were from, for ten points, what country where artists were awarded the Stalin Prize?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Soviet Union",
        "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
        "USSR",
        "CCCP",
        "SSSR"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle was the subject of the Gesta Henrici Quinti, a propaganda piece that has made historians question whether a baggage train was attacked at the beginning or end of this battle. (20 pts)",
        "Stakes and muddy ground hampered the effectiveness of one side’s cavalry in this battle which, like the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Crecy 70 years earlier, reaffirmed the superiority of the longbow. For ten points, name this 1415 battle of the Hundred Years’ War, a victory for England on Saint Crispin’s Day."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
    }
  ]
}